https://youtu.be/S9ocQYIiHqI So what influences jurors?
eet789 23/09/2016 https://youtu.be/S9ocQYIiHqI Điều gì ảnh hưởng tới các bồi thẩm viên?
So I’ve already said that the biggest influence on jurors&#39; decisions is the strength of the
Tôi đã nói rằng điều tác động mạnh nhất tới quyết định của bồi thẩm đoàn là sức mạnh của bằng chứng chống lại bị cáo.
evidence against the defendant. Now we turn to how factors other than the evidence influence
Giờ ta sẽ xem ngoài bằng chứng, những yếu tố khác ảnh hưởng tới bồi thẩm đoàn như thế nào.
jurors&#39; decisions. Obviously these are the things we want to know about so that we can
Ta muốn tìm hiểu về các yếu tố đó nhằm giảm thiểu sức ảnh hưởng của chúng
reduce their effects.
reduce their effects.
Let&#39;s start with the characteristics of the defendant.
Hãy bắt đầu với đặc điểm của bị cáo.
Physically attractive defendants are more likely to be acquitted
Những bị cáo có vẻ ngoài quyến rũ thường được tha bổng hoặc
or receive a lighter sentence. This is true as long as the defendant
nhận những bản án nhẹ hơn người khác. Điều này hoàn toàn đúng,
didn&#39;t use his or her attractiveness to actually carry out the crime. For example by swindling
trừ phi bị cáo sử dụng vẻ ngoài quyến rũ của mình để phạm tội.
someone out of money by romancing them.
Ví dụ như dùng sắc lửa tiền.
The defendant&#39;s race also has an affect the jury. In the United States of America, Black
Chủng tộc của bị cáo cũng ảnh hưởng tới bồi thẩm đoàn.
defendants are more likely to be sent to prison. In fact, racial minorities
Ở Mỹ, các bị cáo da đen thường bị tuyên án tù nhiều hơn. Trong thực tế, các dân tộc thiểu số
are over-represented in custody around the world. For example, not only in the United
có tỷ lệ bị giam giữ khá cao trên thế giới, không chỉ ở Mỹ, mà ở cả Anh và Úc.
States of America, but also in the United Kingdom
States of America, but also in the United Kingdom
and Australia.
and Australia.
There is reasonable evidence from meta-analyses across many studies
Từ phân tích tổng hợp qua nhiều bài nghiên cứu, có thể chứng minh rằng
that there is a main effect of defendant race. This means people from negatively stereotyped
chủng tộc của bị cáo ảnh hưởng nhiều nhất tới quyết định của bồi thẩm đoàn.
racial groups tend to be more likely to be convicted.
Điều này có nghĩa rằng những người nằm trong nhóm chịu định kiến tiêu cực dễ bị kết án hơn.
Ok, so there is evidence that defendants from some categories are seen as being more likely
Tiếp theo là bằng chứng về việc bị cáo từ một số chủng tộc nhất định dễ bị coi là tội phạm hơn.
to be guilty. There is some more research which suggests that the story is more complicated
Tuy vậy có một số nghiên cứu đưa ra các kết quả còn phức tạp hơn thế.
than this, however.
than this, however.
The short story is that defendants seem to be seen as being more likely to be guilty
Một minh chứng ngắn gọn rằng bị cáo bị xem là có khả năng có tội
only when they come from social categories that are stereotypically linked to the features
chỉ khi họ thuộc tầng lớp xã hội có liên quan đến những đặc điểm
of the particular crime they are said to have committed. A good example of this can be seen
tội phạm mà họ đã gây ra.
in research by Gordon and colleagues in 1988.
Một ví dụ điển hình là nghiên cứu của Gordon và đồng nghiệp năm 1988.
In that study, they found that when the defendant’s race matched the type of crime the defendant
Trong nghiên cứu này, họ thấy rằng chủng tộc của bị cáo và tội trạng của bị cáo có một mối liên hệ nhất định
was said to have committed, the defendant was evaluated more negatively. In particular,
tới việc bồi thẩm đoàn kết tội nặng hơn.
a White defendant was punished more than a Black defendant when the alleged crime was
Ví dụ như, một bị cáo da trắng sẽ bị kết tội nặng hơn bị cáo da đen
embezzling money, whereas the opposite was true when the alleged crime was burglary.
khi cả hai biển thủ công quỹ, và ngược lại khi cả hai đều ăn trộm.
You can find another example of exactly the same type of effect in a study by Bodenhausen
Nghiên cứu năm 1990 của Bodenhausen cũng chỉ ra những ví dụ tương tự.
in 1990.
in 1990.
One of the factors that contributes to higher conviction rates in these types of cases was
Một trong những yếu tố góp phần vào tỷ lệ kết án cao trong những loại án thế này được
identified by Jones and Kaplan in 2003. They found that when the defendant matched race-based
xác định bởi Jones và Kaplan vào năm 2003. Họ phát hiện rằng khi bị cáo có các đặc điểm chủng tộc
expectations for the type of crime allegedly committed, mock jurors sought less additional
khớp với chân dung tội phạm được xem là đã gây án, bồi thẩm đoàn sẽ tìm kiếm ít thông tin bổ sung hơn
information to help them make a decision, and instead relied on their pre-existing stereotypes.
để giúp họ đưa ra quyết định, thay vào đó, họ lại kết án dựa trên đặc trưng sẵn có.
We get similar effects based on socio-economic status as well.
Địa vị kinh tế xã hội cũng có đem lại ảnh hưởng tương tự.
So there is reasonable evidence that the reason why people from some racial or ethic groups
Bằng chứng chứng minh là lí do tại sao đôi khi người xuất thân từ nhóm chủng tộc hoặc nhóm tiểu số
are sometimes seen as more likely to be guilty is because stereotypes about those groups
bị coi là có khả năng phạm tội cao là vì định kiến về những nhóm này
are linked to particular types of crime.
gắn với những loại tội phạm cụ thể.
So we know that the defendant&#39;s attractiveness, race, and socio-economic status all influence
Như ta biết, sức quyến rũ, chủng tộc, và địa vị kinh tế xã hội của bị cáo đều
how jurors see them.
ảnh hưởng đến cách bồi thẩm viên kết án.
What about the defendant&#39;s gender?
Vậy còn giới tính của bị cáo?
In a similar vein, non experimental research has found that prosecutors are less likely
Tương tự thế, nghiên cứu phi thực nghiệm cho thấy rằng công tố viên ít khi
to file charges against female than male narcotic offenders, judges are
nộp đơn buộc tội tội phạm ma túy nữ hơn tội phạm ma túy nam, các thẩm phán
more likely to grant women pretrial release than they are to male offenders,
sẽ có khả năng ban lệnh thả nữ tội phạm trước thời hạn hơn so với nam tội phạm,
and women face lower odds of incarceration following trial compared
và sau phiên xét xử, nữ giới chịu mức án tù giam thấp hơn
to men.
so với nam giới.
The relationship between defendant gender and judgements is more complicated. There
Giới tính bị cáo và phán quyết của tòa có mối liên kết rất phức tạp.
doesn&#39;t appear to be a simple overall main effect of defendant gender, except perhaps
Giới tính của bị cáo không phải chỉ là một tác nhân đơn giản, trừ khi
for punishment. Sometimes men are seen as more guilty, and sometimes women are treated
liên quan đến hình phạt. Đôi khi đàn ông bị xem là có tội hơn, và đôi khi phụ nữ
more harshly.
bị đối xử hà khắc hơn.
A good example of the first type of effect can be seen in a meta-analysis across a large
Một ví dụ điển hình cho loại ảnh hưởng đầu tiên thể hiện trong một phân tích tổng hợp qua
number of studies by Dean and colleagues in 2000. That study showed that male defendants
một số lượng lớn nghiên cứu của Dean và đồng nghiệp vào năm 2000. Nghiên cứu cho thấy bị cáo nam
were more likely to be found guilty of some particular types of crimes, particularly assault
dễ bị coi là có tội hơn đối với một số loại tội phạm, cụ thể là hành hung và trộm cắp.
and theft.
and theft.
Another good example of the first type of effect can be seen in research by McCoy and
Một ví dụ điển hình khác cho loại ảnh hưởng đầu tiên có thể thấy trong nghiên cứu của McCoy và
Gray in 2007.
Gray năm 2007.
In this paper, they found that the mock jurors, people pretending to be jurors for the purposes of the study,
Trong báo cáo nghiên cứu, họ nhận thấy rằng những người đóng vai bồi thẩm đoàn vì mục đích nghiên cứu,
believed the victim more when the defendant was described as being a man compared to a
tin tưởng nạn nhân hơn khi biết bị cáo là đàn ông chứ không phải phụ nữ.
woman. In other words, the defendant seemed more guilty when he was a man rather than
Nói cách khác, bị cáo nam có vẻ phạm tội cao hơn so với bị cáo nữ.
a woman.
a woman.
The explanation that is generally given for these types of effects is that men are stereotypically
Lời giải thích đưa ra cho các loại ảnh hưởng này là
seen has having more of the characteristics consistent with being a criminal - in particular,
đàn ông được cho là mang những đặc điểm khớp với tâm tính một tên tội phạm - cụ thể là,
they are seen as more aggressive and assertive and so on.
hung bạo hơn và quyết đoán hơn, v..v
Now, you might be wondering, isn’t it perfectly rational to think that a male defendant is
Có lẽ bạn đang băn khoăn rằng bị cáo nam có khả năng
more likely to be guilty than a female defendant? After all, the vast majority, as in well over
phạm tội cao hơn bị cáo nữ là quá hợp lý còn gì? Sau cùng, đại đa số,
90%, of all people charged and convicted of crimes, especially those involving violence,
hơn 90% những người bị kết án và buộc tội, đặc biệt là tội hành hung, đều là nam.
are men.
are men.
So it seems that the stereotype is based on accurate facts in this particular example—i.e.,
Có vẻ rằng định kiến dựa trên cơ sở thực tế như trong ví dụ này --
the base rate for offending is strongly skewed towards male offenders. Why can’t we just
tỷ lệ căn bản để phạm tội nghiêng hẳn về phía tội phạm nam.
make a probabilistic judgement based on these base rates and convict male defendants?
Tại sao ta không xét xử dựa trên những tỷ lệ xác suất này và kết án bị cáo nam?
Well the problem arises because defendants are not selected at random. When police investigate
Vấn đề là bị cáo không được lựa chọn ngẫu nhiên. Khi cảnh sát điều tra
a crime, they don&#39;t just choose any random person on the street and charge them with
tội phạm, họ không chọn ngẫu nhiên ai đó trên đường và buộc tội người đó.
the offence.
the offence.
Police investigate someone based on non-random factors, for example a tip off, or a witness
Cảnh sát điều tra tội phạm không dựa vào những yếu tố ngẫu nhiên mà dựa vào tin báo, hay danh tính nhân chứng,
identification, and so base rate information is actually irrelevant for deciding whether
vậy thông tin tỷ lệ căn bản không hề liên quan đến quyết định kết án bị cáo.
the defendant is guilty or not. Thus, jurors should make their decisions based only the
Hơn nữa, bồi thẩm đoàn chỉ nên quyết định dựa trên
evidence presented at trial.
chứng cứ đưa ra tại tòa.
Now on the other hand, there is evidence that sometimes female defendants are treated more
Mặt khác, có bằng chứng chứng minh rằng đôi khi bị cáo nữ bị đối xử
harshly compared to male defendants.
hà khắc hơn so với bị cáo nam.
Wayne and colleagues in 2001 found that a woman who sexually harassed a man was viewed
Wayne cùng đồng nghiệp vào năm 2001 đã phát hiện rằng phụ nữ quấy rối tình dục đàn ông
more negatively than a man who sexually harassed a woman, possibly due to stereotypes about
sẽ bị đánh giá tiêu cực hơn so với đàn ông quấy rối tình dục phụ nữ, có thể vì định kiến về
traditional sex roles and sexual aggressiveness.
vai trò giới tính truyền thống và tính hung hăng tình dục.
Viki and colleagues in 2005 found that a female who murdered a number of children was evaluated
Năm 2005, Viki và đồng nghiệp phát hiện rằng phụ nữ sát hại nhiều trẻ em sẽ bị người tham dự nghiên cứu,
more negatively by participants who scored higher on a measure of sexism.
những người có thành kiến giới tính cao, đánh giá cực đoan hơn.
There is also some evidence that women get evaluated more negatively because they seem
Có một số bằng chứng cho thấy phụ nữ bị đánh giá cực đoan hơn bởi họ có vẻ
to be &#39;out of place&#39; in the criminal justice system, and so their behaviour
không thuộc về hệ thống tư pháp hình sự, bởi thế hành vi của họ
is seen as particularly abnormal.
được xem là đặc biệt sai trái.
So why might these types of effects reverse in this way?
Tại sao mức ảnh hưởng của những yếu tố này lại đảo ngược như thế?
Well, there are a few possible reasons.
Có một vài lí do có thể xảy ra.
The first has to do with how we think about men and women in comparison to gender-based
Lí do đầu tiên liên quan đến cách ta nghĩ về nam và nữ so với tiêu chuẩn về giới tính
standards and the types of questions we are asking ourselves.
và những loại câu hỏi ta tự đặt ra cho bản thân.
A zero-sum or absolute judgment task, like deciding whether the defendant is guilty or
Nhiệm vụ phán quyết bù trừ hay tuyệt đối, như quyết định liệu bị cáo có tội hay không,
not, will tend to encourage seeing the defendant in terms of the stereotype associated with
thường sẽ góp phần vào cách nhìn nhận bị cáo theo định kiến.
them. For example, when thinking about the guilt of a male defendant, we might think
Ví dụ, khi nghĩ về tội trạng của bị cáo nam, có lẽ ta nghĩ
he is guilty because we see him in terms of the male stereotype which is more consistent
anh ta có tội bởi ta nhìn nhận anh ta theo loại định kiến nhất quán với tâm tính tội phạm.
with the attributes of a criminal.
with the attributes of a criminal.
When the task is a subjective one in that we are asking ourselves how much of some attribute
Khi đó là một nhiệm vụ chủ quan, ta tự hỏi bị cáo có bao nhiêu đặc điểm khớp với tâm tính tội phạm,
a defendant has, for example how aggressive the defendant&#39;s behaviour was, then we contrast
chẳng hạn như hành vi của bị cáo hung hăng thế nào, sau đó ta đối chiếu
their behaviour with our expectations for their gender. In this case, we would see a
hành vi của họ với thành kiến giới tính. Trong trường hợp này, ta sẽ xem
female defendant&#39;s behaviour as being more aggressive than a male defendant&#39;s behaviour,
hành vi của bị cáo nữ hung hăng hơn so với hành vi của bị cáo nam,
even if they had both objectively acted in exactly the same way. This is called shifting
ngay cả khi, khách quan mà nói, cả hai đều gây án theo cùng một cách.
standards.
Đây được gọi là tiêu chuẩn luân phiên.
The final reason is related to thinking about jurors as cognitive optimisers. We talked
Lý do cuối cùng liên quan đến việc nghĩ bồi thẩm đoàn là người lạc quan hóa nhận thức.
about this in the previous video. Remember we talked about how when a defendant is stereotypical,
Ta đã bàn về điều này trong bài học trước. Bạn có nhớ rằng, ta đã nói về khi nào bị cáo bị đánh giá qua định kiến,
perceivers have more cognitive capacity to think about other things, such as the strength
người có khả năng nhận thức cao hơn khi nghĩ về những thứ khác, chẳng hạn như sức mạnh
of the evidence against the defendant.
bằng chứng chống lại bị cáo.
This means that when the case is strong, jurors will be more likely to convict the defendant,
Điều này có nghĩa, khi vụ án rõ ràng, bồi thẩm đoàn sẽ dễ kết án bị cáo hơn,
and when the case is weak, they will be more likely to acquit. Now because female defendants
và khi vụ án mờ mịt, có khả năng cao họ sẽ tuyên bố trắng án. Bởi bị cáo nữ
can&#39;t easily be represented by a stereotype, jurors should be relatively insensitive to
không thể dễ thể hiện qua định kiến, bồi thẩm đoàn nên cực kì nhạy cảm
the strength of the case against the female defendant. And so, when the case is weak,
với sức mạnh của vụ án chống lại bị cáo nữ. Và khi vụ án không rõ ràng,
jurors should tend to acquit the male more compared to the female defendant. And the
bồi thẩm viên thường nên tuyên bố bị cáo nam trắng án hơn so với bị cáo nữ.
opposite should happen when the case is strong.
Trường hợp ngược lại xảy ra khi vụ án có chứng cứ rõ ràng
Right, so we&#39;ve spent a bit of time talking about how the defendant&#39;s attributes can influence
Được rồi, ta đã dành một chút thời gian bàn về việc tâm tính của bị cáo có thể ảnh hưởng
how jurors evaluate them. Now while these can be pretty difficult to change, research
tới cách bồi thẩm đoàn định tội họ thế nào. Giờ trong khi những đặc điểm này khó có thể thay đổi,
is starting to identify some of the ways to potentially reduce their effects.
nghiên cứu đang bắt đầu xác định một số cách để giảm thiểu sức ảnh hưởng của chúng.
We probably don&#39;t have the time to get into those now, as we could spend another whole
Chúng ta có lẽ không có thời gian đào sâu những điều này, nhưng ta có thể dành một khóa học khác
course talking about how to reduce the effects of stereotypes.
bàn về cách giảm thiểu sức ảnh hưởng của định kiến.
But we can turn our eye to something that influences jurors&#39; verdicts, and that is also
Nhưng ta có thể chuyển hướng tập trung đến thứ ảnh hưởng đến phán quyết của bồi thẩm đoàn,
actually pretty easy to change.
và điều đó khá dễ đổi.
We are talking about the order in which jurors are asked to decide verdicts in cases involving
Ta đang nói về thứ tự bồi thẩm đoàn được yêu cầu đưa ra phán quyết trong những vụ án cần nhiều hơn một phán quyết.
more than one verdict.
more than one verdict.
This can happen, for example, in a murder case. A jury might be asked to decide whether
Chuyện này có thể xảy ra, ví dụ, trong một vụ sát nhân. Một bồi thẩm viên có thể được yêu cầu đưa ra quyết định
the defendant is guilty of murder, and if not murder, manslaughter, and if not that,
bị cáo có giết người hay không, và nếu không giết người, giết người, và nếu không phải thế,
perhaps some lesser charge.
có lẽ sẽ nhận án nhẹ hơn
Greenberg, Williams and O&#39;Brien in 1986 gave participants a condensed version of a murder
Greenberg, Williams và O' Brien vào năm 1986 đã đưa cho người tham dự một bản giải thích súc tích về vụ án giết người.
trial. The possible verdicts were first degree murder, second degree murder, voluntary manslaughter,
Những phán quyết có thể được đưa trong vụ án giết người cấp độ một, cấp độ hai, cố ý giết người,
involuntary manslaughter, or not guilty.
không cố ý giết người, hay vô tội.
After being given about six pages of judicial instructions by the experimenter, participants
Sau khi xem xét sáu trang hướng dẫn tư pháp nhà thí nghiệm đưa ra, người tham gia
were asked to consider the verdicts either from harshest to most lenient, as is usual
được yêu cầu cân nhắc phán quyết từ nặng nhất tới khoan dung nhất,
in murder trials, or from most lenient to harshest.
trong những phiên tòa xét xử vụ án giết người, hoặc từ khoan dung nhất tới nặng nhất.
Results showed that participants gave harsher verdicts when they were asked to consider
Kết quả cho thấy người tham gia đưa ra phán quyết nặng hơn khi họ được yêu cầu cân nhắc
&#39;the first degree murder’ as the first possible verdict option compared to when they
giết người cấp độ một là khả năng phán quyết đầu tiên, so với khi họ
were asked to consider &#39;not guilty&#39; as the first possible verdict option.
được yêu cầu cân nhắc vô tội cho khả năng phán quyết đầu tiên.
Greenberg and colleagues thought that this was due to a confirmation bias, which is the
Greenberg và đồng nghiệp nghĩ rằng nguyên nhân do thiên kiến xác nhận,
idea that when given a hypothesis to test, we tend to look for information that confirms,
có nghĩa là khi nhận một giả thuyết để kiểm tra, ta thường tìm kiếm thông tin xác nhận,
rather than contradicts, that hypothesis. So when participants were given a hypothesis
hơn là đối lập, giả thuyết đó. Khi người tham gia nhận được một giả thuyết
by the first proposed verdict option, they focussed on the evidence in the case that
cho lựa chọn phán quyết đầu tiên được đề xuất, họ tập trung vào bằng chứng mà
was consistent with that verdict. When given First Degree Murder as the first verdict,
nhất quán với phán quyết. Khi đưa ra phán quyết đầu tiên là giết người cấp độ một,
participants were more influenced by evidence suggesting guilt. When given &#39;not guilty&#39;
người tham gia sẽ bị ảnh hưởng bởi bằng chứng khẳng định có tội. Khi đưa ra phán quyết đầu tiên là vô tội,
as the first verdict, they were more influenced by evidence suggesting that defendant was
họ sẽ bị ảnh hưởng bởi bằng chứng khẳng định bị cáo vô tội.
innocent.
innocent.
So that&#39;s a number of things that influence individual&#39;s decisions. One thing we haven&#39;t
Đó là một số thứ ảnh hưởng đến quyết định của một cá nhân. Một thứ khá được quan tâm
talked about that has received quite a deal of attention in the research is expert evidence.
trong nghiên cứu mà ta chưa nói đến là chứng cứ của chuyên gia.
While stereotypes and schemas are important for how we evaluate expert testimony, it is
Trong khi định kiến và sơ đồ quan trọng với cách ta đánh giá bằng chứng chuyên môn,
worth spending a bit more time in the next video talking about this type of testimony
dành thêm một chút thời gian trong video sắp tới bàn về loại bằng chứng này rất đáng giá
because there are some additional unique issues to do with experts and their testimony.
bởi có một số vấn đề kì lạ cần bàn với chuyên gia và bằng chứng của họ